

□ 630-624-9699 | Sernasek@gmail.com | Asbernasek.com | San Francisco Bay Area

Overview

Data scientist whose efforts to understand and predict the behavior of complex systems have yielded several academic publications and issued patents. Brings a unique blend of creativity, math and science literacy, and engineering pragmatism, all backed by strong python scripting skills and a healthy dose of common sense. Recently concluded 5 years of academic research preceded by 3 years working at a midstage startup, and is now seeking new opportunities to continue learning while contributing to something fun.

Expertise includes:

- **Developing useful models** to analyze and simulate complex processes.
- Empowering decisions with quantitative insight backed by rigorous analysis.
- Building rich data sets by turning qualitative observations into quantitative measurements.
- Hacking together data-driven solutions to a wide variety of everyday problems.
- Identifying and prototyping state of the art methods derived from the research literature.
- Collaborating with multidisciplinary teams to coordinate multifaceted R&D efforts.
- Bridging the gap between research, engineering, and business by emphasizing broader implications of technical nuance.

Skills_

Programming python / cython / pandas, scipy, sklearn, etc. / visualization / package development / git / LaTeX / HTML & CSS / Unix shell Data Engineering feature selection / dimensionality reduction / images / natural language / structured text / web scraping Analysis hypothesis testing / Bayesian inference / signal detection / clustering / time series / networks Modeling dynamical systems / stochastic processes / nonlinear regression / classification / reduced-order models / process simulation Computer Vision feature extraction / image segmentation / spatial analysis / quantitative microscopy

Education

Ph.D. in Chemical and Biological Engineering Northwestern University

2014 - 2019

• Dissertation combined data science and chemical engineering to explore how cells make reliable decisions.

B.S. in Chemical Engineering • High Honors University of California, Santa Barbara

2008 - 2012

Experience _____

Consulting (while traveling!)

Present

- Built a database of 5k+ targeted B2B sales leads using a combination of web-scraping, commercial APIs, and machine learning.
- · Provided data-driven insight that enabled a recruiting firm to boost their monthly revenue by focusing on more probable hires.
- Automated several text content extraction and parsing routines to save hundreds of hours of tedious labor.

Researcher at Northwestern University Evanston, IL

2014 - 2019

- Published in high profile journals including Cell and PLOS Computational Biology.
- · Designed, built, and deployed several simulation and analysis frameworks for the research community.
- Discovered a surprising link between expression dynamics and metabolism by developing a model that predicts developmental mistakes.
- Discovered a novel cell decision mechanism by using computer vision to derive insight from microscopy data.
- Increased data volume and quality by developing a computer vision pipeline for automated microscopy analysis.
- Mentored (and learned from) two inspiring young researchers in formulating their own projects.

Process Engineer at LanzaTech Chicago, IL

2012 - 2014

- Developed renewable energy process design concepts, earning two granted patents and further pending applications.
- · Designed and built the company's core process modeling framework, which was rapidly adopted by all engineers.
- · Collaborated with technology providers to identify complementary value streams, leading to corporate partnerships.
- Modeled refinery-scale processes to predict and optimize economic and life-cycle performance.
- Advised executives and investors with technical analysis that directly inspired major strategic decisions.

Research Assistant at UC Santa Barbara Santa Barbara, CA

2011 - 2012

• Conducted first ever dynamic measurement of interaction forces between vesicles. Published in Soft Matter